Okay, let us consider a few more examples.
And I will start with this addition
function that I defined in the slides on
the natural numbers, as defined
there, as a recursive datatype.
And the one thing I want to briefly show here is
just an example of how computation works now
with this function on the natural numbers.
Of course, this will not be vastly
different from the earlier example
with the Connection and matching inside
the Connection to compute the travel time.
But anyway, let's do this briefly.
So, let's say we want to add two numbers.
So, that would correspond
to an expression like this.
So, we have the addition, which is
a function that takes two arguments,
and these arguments are natural numbers.
So, let's say we want to
add 2, or maybe 3 plus 2.
So, the left argument would be 3.
But of course, tree is a datatype
expression with these data constructors.
So, basically, this would be such
a very simple, namely linear, tree
with three successor constructors
and the zero constructor, right?
This corresponds to the natural
number 3 encoded in this datatype.
And actually, let me do this just with 2.
So that the computation doesn't get too long.
So, let me really add 2 and 2.
So, then on both sides, I would have
the same tree (the same expression).
Okay.
Then how does the computation work?
Well, as before, we need to
check which case to take.
So, we have the addition function,
we have two rules for that.
The first one apparently doesn't apply because
zero does not match against
successor (Succ) successfully.
So, of course, it is the second
equation that could be used.
And what would this mean?
Well, the first argument is
the successor of something.
And the something is called 'n'.
So, actually, this means that
this part would be bound to 'n'.
And the second argument of the
addition is just a variable.
So, the whole second argument
would be considered to be 'm'.
Okay, so this is this part, and then we have 'm'
and 'n' as the arguments or parts of arguments.
Okay, so with this binding, this equation
matches. We take the right-hand side.
What does the right-hand side say?
So, how do we replace this?
Well, we replace this by a
“successor of” (Succ) and an “add” call.
So, successor is a function which is applied
to this add call… to this other expression.
So, what is this add?
Well, it's a call of two arguments.
What are the two arguments,
'n' and 'm'? Well, we know what 'n' and 'm' are
because they appeared here.
So, this will now be a
call with the left argument
successor of zero (Succ Zero) and the right argument
successor of successor of zero (Succ (Succ Zero)).
So, that's this Zero here.
Okay, then how does it go on?
Well, now, again, we have this addition call.
Which should compute something so
it doesn't use the first equation,
because the first argument is not Zero.
So, it, of course, takes
again the second equation.
And what does it match?
Well, now this will be 'n'.
And this will be 'm'.
Yes.
So, this goes on as “successor of addition of n
and m”. With this situation that we have here,
with the successor of 'n' and 'm', we should use
another successor call and then
a recursive call of addition.
So, we get successor of successor
of another addition call.
And what are the two
arguments of this call?
It's just a Zero from this place
and the 'm' which is actually still, now and always
actually in this call, successor of successor of Zero.
Okay, and now how does it further go on?
Well, now we have to evaluate this call.
Now, the first argument is Zero.
So, it won't match the second equation anymore.
It will match the first equation.
And what does the first equation say?
It says addition of Zero and
something is that something.
Okay?
Which means that this will now actually
reduce further… evaluate further, too.
And now this is the Zero and this
is, of course, still the 'm'.
So, the next step will be "successor of successor
of" and then this expression, we call as 'm'.
Then we are done.
Because there are no further function calls left.
And what have you computed?
We have computed, two plus two is four.
It would have been disappointing if
this had not worked out this way.
Okay, so this was something I wanted to show.
And then also, I wanted to show
just a few more examples of
values of datatypes, in particular in the
case where we had these polymorphic datatypes.
So, what did we have?
So, for example, we had this Tree datatype in the
slides and there was this
version, which was polymorphic.
Yes, which started something like:
“Tree a =” and then the definition
as on slides.
The one where we had this polymorphic version.
And then we can, for example,
ask ourselves for a few values.
Well, for example, we could
ask ourselves, what are values
of type “Tree Integer”?
And well, then we have values
like a Leaf, or a Node
with two arguments, where the first
and last should be integer Trees again.
So, they could of course also be Leaf.
And then here, we have something like
5, because it's an integer, right?
This tells us that you have a number here.
For example, this one, and then of course,
there can be more nesting involved.
So, you could have Node, let's again
say, 5 and a Leaf as the left part.
In the right, we may have another Node.
Maybe this now, again, has leaves as
successors. And here, we could have 7.
So, we can't have a Boolean value there, right?
If we have a Tree Integer, then at all
these places, we will have integers.
We can have a Tree of Bools, then we can have
False and True and False and False and whatever,
but at each place the same thing.
That's how this parameter is
used and the effect it has.
Okay, so this is something.
And then maybe let's also look at something
where we combine this with this “Maybe” type,
which was another polymorphic type.
And its argument type could, for
example, be a Tree type, right?
So, let's look at something like this.
Just for the sake of examples. There
is the following type: “Maybe”...
That was this type constructor.
And then we could put some type here.
And of course, we can nest this arbitrarily.
So, for example, you could put there a Tree type.
Well, and let's not take Tree Integer.
Let's take Tree Bool.
Okay, now this Tree Bool that
would be trees like this,
but with Trues and Falses
instead of fives and sevens.
Now, actually, it occurs
as Maybe of Tree Bools.
So, it can't be such a Tree directly.
So, for example, one possible value
of this type would be Nothing.
So, we don't have a Tree.
We have Nothing.
That's one of the two data constructors
of the Maybe type constructor.
But of course, you could also
have the Just case and then
the construction was that: Maybe of
something could be Nothing or Just
and then something of that thing,
which is the type argument of Maybe.
So, for example, you can have Just a Leaf, or we can
have Just and then a Node tree with two leaves (Leaf),
and now, of course, a Boolean
value in the middle position
because of this: Maybe Tree Bool.
The Maybe leads to this Just
and Tree Bool is this part.
And of course, this goes on.
Right, you can put further Just
and some Tree there with structures
like this or other nesting structures,
but of course, always Boolean values instead
of numbers in the label places for each node.